<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A light for the ignorant or A treatise shevving, that in the nevv Testament, is set forth three kingly states or governments, that is, the civill state, the true ecclesiasticall state, and the false ecclesiasticall state</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103338</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3491</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05460)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3491)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1245:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A light for the ignorant or A treatise shevving, that in the nevv Testament, is set forth three kingly states or governments, that is, the civill state, the true ecclesiasticall state, and the false ecclesiasticall state</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richt Right Press] Seene and allowed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Authority --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3491:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3491:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LIGHT FOR THE IGNORANT OR A Treatiſe ſhevving, that in the nevv Teſtament, is ſet forth three Kingly States or Governments, that is, the Civill State, the true Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall-State, and the falſe Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall State.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 15.13.</bibl>
               <p>Every plant which my Heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhalbe rooted vp.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3491:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader,</head>
            <p>VVell affectionated Reader. It is (as thou knoweſt) a divine precept, that we ſhould <hi>giue Honour to whom honour is due:</hi> Jmplying therein, that no honour is due either to Perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or things, but in a lawfull and right way. And hence it is that many of Gods deare Servants both haue and ſtill doe, refuſe to yeeld any Reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Honoor, Service, &amp;c. vnto
<hi>Archbiſhops Biſhops:</hi> and their dependent Offices; I ſay, as they are <hi>Eccleſiaſticall perſons</hi> &amp; doe adminiſter in their
<hi>Spirituall Courts</hi> as they terme them: in regard they have aſſumed ſuch a <hi>State</hi> as is to ſpeake properly and truely of it, neither
<hi>Iure Divino</hi> nor <hi>jure Humano,</hi> warrented by the word of God. But of this I ſhall not need to ſay any more, in regard thou ſhalt find what here I ſay cleared &amp; proved ſufficiently: viz. that their calling is not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, either in <hi>a divine or humane respect,</hi> but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſcripturs after mentioned: altogether &amp; every way from the Devill. And therfore look unto it whoſoever thou art, that thou (like
<hi>Mordecay</hi>) bow not the knee to any of theſe <hi>Amaliks,</hi> but on the contrarie <hi>Feare God and honour the King,</hi> and give reverence Only to ſuch ordinances as God binds thy Conſcience too, either in reſpect of nature or grace, and ſoe doeing thou ſhalt <hi>Give vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, And give vnto God, thoſe things that are Gods.</hi> And that thou mayſt ſo doe, the Lord ſanctſfie both this and all other good meanes and helps to thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:3491:2"/>A LIGHT FOR THE IGNORANT OR A Treatiſe ſhevving, that in the nevv Teſtament, is ſet forth three Kingly States or Governments, that is, the Civill State, the true Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall-State, and the falſe Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall State.</head>
         <div type="premises">
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are in the new Teſtement of Chriſt Ieſus three Kinglie States or Governments. The Civill State. The true Eccleſiaſticall State. And the falſe Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall State. Two of them are of God, and the third is of the Divill. They all conſiſt of theſe Seven par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars following.</p>
            <p>In the Firſt, place theſe three pollitique Regiments hath each of them a King or Head over them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They haue each of them authoritie power or ſtate pollitique.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They haue books and Charters, wherein their ſtatutes, Lawes, and Cannons are writen.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Each of theſe make themſelves Citties Corporations or bodies politique.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, They haue Officers and deputies who are their ſeuerall Miniſters to and in there bodies or Corporations.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, They have Lawes, ordinances, and adminiſtrations for theſe officers to adminiſter to their ſubjects, according to there ſeverall functions in the name and by the power of their proper King, and head; from whom they haue received their authority &amp; in whoſe name they adminiſter.</p>
            <p>Sevenlie, and laſtlie, they haue ſubjects or members governed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3491:3"/>by and in their ſeuerall pollitique States and powers vnder their ſeverall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eads.</p>
            <div n="1" type="particular">
               <head>The Firſt particular Handled. Theſe haue each of them a King or Head over them.</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State.</head>
                  <p>The Firſt is the State of Magiſtracie or civill State, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Ceſar is to haue his due as King and head, theſe Kings &amp; heads are to be prayed for of all Gods people, as their Heads and gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nours
<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.2 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State:</head>
                  <p>This ſtate is Chriſts the annointed <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.6.
<hi>Acts.</hi> 2.26. whome God the Father hath ſet upon the Throne of
<hi>David, Jſay,</hi> 9.6.7. and he is King of Saints <hi>Rev.</hi> 15,3. Yea the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> &amp; <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords. Rev.</hi>
17.14. &amp; 19,16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>The third is the heliſh ſtate of the Beaſt, his Kingdome or ſtate of Rome, which in the 13. <hi>Rev. v.</hi> 2. is ſaid to haue his power from the Devill; alſo he is ſaid to haue a Throne: therefore hee is a King 11. c. He is called the King of the Locuſts which is there ſaid to bee the Angell of the bottomleſſe pit. v. 11.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="particular">
               <head>Secondly, theſe haue each of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Kingly ſtate or power pollitique</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State.</head>
                  <p>This power or Civill ſtate is of God, and is the Charracter of Gods ſoveraigntie over man; is diſplaid by his Communicating the ſame unto Kings &amp; ſuch as are in authority under them, for which cauſe hee hath ſaid yee are Gods, and God muſt and is obeyed by ſtooping and ſubmitting to this power and ſtate, and he that reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this power reſiſteth the ordinance of God <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>Likewiſe this ſtate is of God, for it is the Kingdome of his deare Sonne, &amp; is not the Civill ſtate but the Eccleſiaſtical ſtate of Chriſt his Church, or power which he received of his Father <hi>Mat</hi>
28.18, after that he roſe again from the dead, by which power he au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed his Apoſtles &amp; ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on his errand or meſſage to al the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. which power the Apoſtles vſed in planting Churchs <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3491:3"/>and Church Officers, which power Chriſt gives to all the Churches of the Saints to the end of the world, it is the power given to them to bind and looſe too, and from the Devill, and to right each others wrongs <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. it is the ſame power and ſtate the Churches had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to them by the Apoſtles who reproved the Churches for not uſing it to ſuppreſſe ſinne and ſinne rs 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. with the ſeuen Churches in <hi>Aſia. Rev.</hi> 2.3. c. theſe and many more are the ſeverall vſes the Lord hath made of this true Eccleſiaſticall or Church ſtate, and Goverment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>This Angell of the Bottemleſſe pit <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. the King of the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts hath a ſtate, throne, power, and great authority.
<hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. &amp; in the ſame Chapter it is ſaid, he hath power to continue 42 moneths, v. 5. that is 126. dayes as c. 12.6. counting each day for a yeare (as the Lord doth in numbers, 14.34. and Ezec. 4.6,) it is 1260. yeares that is the length or time of his Raigne, that one and the ſame time which Chriſts Kingdome vnder the name of the holie City ſhalbe trod under foot
<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. Likewiſe that is that power or ſtate that the woman or great whore ſits or rids uppon: whereby ſhee is able to Raigne
<hi>Rev.</hi> 13.16. &amp;c. 17. as a <hi>Queene</hi> over the Kings of the earth. And Laſtly, this ſtate is ſoe great that it <hi>Captiuates</hi> all <hi>Kings Princes</hi> &amp; <hi>Emperours,</hi> yea all the world of vngodly men <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7.8. wonders, followes, and worſhips this ſtate, or beaſt, and if they will not he hath ſuch power and authority that hee will compell high and low, rich and poore, bond and free, to ſubmit unto him, &amp; to kill all thoſe that are found refractory to his ſtate and power. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.15.16.17. This is the Falſe Eccleſiaſticall ſtate and power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="particular">
               <head>Thirdly, theſe haue each of them bookes and Chartors to declare their minds to their Subjects.</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, all Kings &amp; governours haue Bookes, ſtatutes, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, wherein are recorded their Lawes Articles, Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, likewiſe to Citties and townes Corporated they give Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors whereby they haue power and preuilidge from their King, &amp; head, in his name and power to inſtate themſelves into divers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3491:4"/>for their mutuall good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>Even ſoe in the next place Ghriſt Jeſus hath given his lawes vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> &amp; his ſtatutes to <hi>Iſraell,</hi> his ſtatute Books are the Holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Old and New Teſtament, he is faithfull in all his houſe as was <hi>Moſes Heb.</hi> 3.2.6. the acts of his laſt Parliament which hee called for the eſtabliſhing of his Kingdome, when hee was 40. daies with his Diſciples giving them lawes through the Holy Ghoſt, even till hee was taken vp into Heaven in their ſight, as wee may ſee in <hi>Acts.</hi> 1. <hi>chapt.</hi> Thoſe bookes called the
<hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the Epiſtles and the
<hi>Revelation,</hi> in theſe the Cities and Charters of the new Jeruſalem is to be found with the previledges thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to belonging.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>This ſmoaky pollitique State of the Crowned Locuſts or Roman Clergie <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.3.7. hath diſtinct bookes from the other two ſtates that are of God, for this State or power hath Bookes of Cannons, Counſels, bookes of Articles, bookes of Ordination of Prieſts and Deacons, with the booke of Homilies, and the Booke of Common-prayer, and the power and ſtate of this Beaſt, doth more narrowly looke that all be agreeable to theſe bookes then the other two ſtates doth (as is manifeſt by that ſtrict eye that is had ouer all in every pariſh) not onelie in forraigne Lands, but eveu in this our <hi>Kingdome of England,</hi> for they of this Kingdome of Darkeneſſe are wiſer &amp; more diligent in their generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children of light.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="particular">
               <head>Fourthly, by vertue of theſe Charters, theſe three ſtates make Citties and Corporations, according to their proper &amp; diſtinct ſtate &amp; power pollitique.</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State.</head>
                  <p>Jn the next place the loyall Subjects of this Regiment vnder their King &amp; Head, by vertue of theſe Charters, become famous Citties, &amp; other inferior corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s agreeable to the tenour of their ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Charters that they received from their Head, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their Charters then &amp; by that means they received the State &amp; power to become a Citty or Corperation vnder that Head, &amp; when they haue vnited or incorporated themſelvs into a Bodie they are a Citty conſtituted,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3491:4"/>and this ſtate &amp; power they are entered into, is their forme and being, and nothing elſe doth diſtinguiſh them from their former ſtate and condition but that power and ſtate, that is, their ſtate wherein they live moue and haue their being pollitiquely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>In like manner the Subjects of this heavenlie regiment or King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, by power from him their Head, doe become viſible Churches and bodies incorporated together in his name &amp; power <hi>Mat.</hi>
18. therefore the Church hee left behind him of 120. were of one accord Acts 1. and to them were vnited or joyned 3000. in the next chapt. ſo the ſaints at
<hi>Antioch,</hi> became a body or Church whoſe conſtitution or incorporation wee may ſee to bee a joyning themſelves to the Lord Acts.
11.2.23. ſoe all the Churches of the Saints became bodies pollitique, and therefore Gods viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are called Citties or the City of God
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.1.2.8. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi>
87.2.3. Therefore the Saints are called Cittizens <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. Inhabitants of the Living God <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. This holy Cittie is troden under foote 42. Moneths <hi>Re.</hi> 11.2. the time of the Raigne of the Beaſt (<hi>Re.</hi> 13.5.) whoſe Raigne is juſt ſo long &amp; this Holy Citty is the <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> that comes downe from heaven in great glory <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. the forme or beeing of his divine Citty or ſpirituall Bodie is the ſtate and power pollitique inſtituted by Chriſt and given to his Saints <hi>Jude,</hi> 3. <hi>v. Pſal.</hi> 133. and thus under Chriſt as their King they live, moue and haue their being pollitiquelie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>So the power of Satan the Devil by hath the wiſdome of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Beaſt, or falſe Prophet, not only made to himſelfe a great Citty whoſe power killed Chriſt Rev. 11.8. Thereby pointing vs to the Roman power that ſtill kills his Saints, for this Citty is ſoe pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that ſhe Raigns over the Kings of the earth, &amp; maks them to drinke of the cup of her fornications, till they be ſo drunke thereby that they become her ſervants Rev. 17.2.18. &amp;
18.2. And by this falſe Eccleſiaſticall power &amp; ſtate, there are made leſſe Citties called the Citties of the nations o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (nation Churches) &amp; are of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Re.
16.9. as Daughters to the whore &amp; Mother of fornication of the earth, this falſe great Catholique Church is diſtributed into<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3491:5"/>nations, provinces, and into every dioceſſe and parriſh, as liuely and apparent as the Civill ſtate, is in every parriſh and in every Houſe therein, ſoe that they live moue and haue their beeing as Royallie from this Beaſtlike power as the Saints doe by Chriſt, or ſubjects under their King, this is plaine by the daily troubles the poore ſaints ſuffer in every parriſh if they worſhip not as this power com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mands.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="particular">
               <head>Fiftly Theſe haue each of them proper and diſtinct officers belonging to each pollitique State.</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State.</head>
                  <p>In the firſt place theſe Cities by vertue of their Chartors, injoy their owne officers, <hi>Mayors, Shirrifes, Aldermen,</hi> and other inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Officers as their Lord and King hath allotted them, and alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour corporations according as is granted to them in their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and they that obey theſe doe well and pleaſe God in keeping the firſt Commandement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiasticall State?</head>
                  <p>Likewiſe the Citty of God by vertue of their chartor haue right to enjoy their owne Biſhops, ouerſeeres or Elders <hi>Acts,</hi>
14.23. and <hi>chap,</hi> 20. <hi>Titus,</hi> 1.5,7. Which are not many, yet Wiſdome that hath built her houſe hath found them to be ſufficient: which are theſe, <hi>Paſtors, Teachers. Elders, Deacons, Widdowes, Rom.</hi>
12.7.8. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.12. <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> and they that obey theſe and theſe onely ſerve Chriſt and obey God in keeping the 2. and 3. Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, theſe only being the officers which God by his Holy Apoſtles hath ſet up, inſtituted and placed in his Church to the end of the world: therefore, in Hearing, and obeying theſe we heare &amp; obey Chriſt that ſent them <hi>Luke.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.40</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The falſe Eccleſiasticall State?</head>
                  <p>In like manner hath this whoriſh City, or Citties, the Falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or Body of falſe prophets attending upon their forged diviſes, &amp; humane adminiſtrations, which are almoſt innumirable to reckon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope to the pariſh clark or Paritor whoſoever obyes theſe or any of theſe breaks the three. firſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, for in hearing &amp; obeying theſe they hear &amp; obey the Dragon, Beaſt, &amp; whore, that ſent them and gaue them their authority and Office, that as Realie as<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3491:5"/>wee Heare and obey the King by ſtooping and ſubmitting to a
<hi>Constable:</hi> who ſees not this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="particular">
               <head>Theſe haue each of them proper and ſeverall lawes, ſtatutes, ordinances, and adminiſtrations for their ſeverall offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to attend vpon.</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State</head>
                  <p>Sixtly, In this ſtate or in theſe Citties are the lawes and ordinances of men, that the ſaints muſt obey in the Lord, for though in the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtels there were no Chriſtian Kings, yet the Churches of the Saints were commanded to obey their Lawes, Religious Lawes they could not bee, Becauſe the Magiſtrates were all infidells, therefore the
<hi>Apostle Peter</hi> diſtinguſheth them from the Divine, by calling them the Ordinances of men, due vnto Cae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſar, as divine obedience is unto God,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſtcall State.</head>
                  <p>Even ſo this Cittie of God with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> officers are to obſerue what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoever Chriſt hath commanded them <hi>Math.</hi> 28.20. the Church of
<hi>Corinth</hi> kept them 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. and <hi>Paulls</hi> Charge to
<hi>Timothy is to teach the Church to obſerue all without prefering one before another, as he would anſwer it before Chriſt Ieſus and his Elect Angells.</hi> Theſe divine things are due to Chriſt Ieſus, and to him &amp; to him onely, belongs this viſible worſhip <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4
21.22.23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The falſe Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>The Lawes &amp; adminiſtrations of this whoriſh Church, are partly their owne Inventions, contained in the Bookes formerly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, with ſome divine truthes which vſurped they injoy, which truthes they vſe as a help to ſet a gloſe vpon their inventions: that they may paſſe with a better acceptation, but both Divine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed are conſecrated &amp; dedicated by the Beaſt, and are adminiſtr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Officers and power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="particular">
               <head>Seauentlhy, All theſe three haue their ſubjects or people which their pollitique Bodies conſiſt of.</head>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Civill State</head>
                  <p>Laſtly, this State hath Subjects, which are the Kings alleiged people, and are bound to him their Head, by the Oath of alleig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; as any of them do purchaſe a Charter from him to become<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3491:6"/>a Cittie or Corporation, they are bound by vertue of their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to walke ſubmiſſiuely to him their pollitique head, and in that relation are by duty bound to keepe the Lawes of their Charters in his name &amp; power, which is their pollitique obedience.</p>
                  <p>This Ciuill State is Gods Ordinance, and is here borrowed to Jlluſtrate, manifeſt, and ſet forth the other two in the former per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler, and ſoe we leaue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State,</head>
                  <p>Soe in the laſt place, the Subjects of this State are only Saints &amp; noe other, that is ſuch as by the Rule of the word are to be Judged one of another to be in Chriſt, otherwiſe they haue no right to this Kingdome 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Chapt.</hi> 5.13. But are intruders
<hi>Iud.</hi> 4. verſe and ſoe not of the Kingdome, though in the Kingdome,
1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19 and the Saints are out of their places till they come within this Holy Citty.</p>
                  <p>To this State all Gods people are Called, both out of this world and all falſe Churches, eſpecially from this Regiment of darkeneſſe there diſcribed 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiasticall State</head>
                  <p>Laſtly, the Subjects of this Kingdome of darkenes are all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitans of the Earth, Kings &amp; ſubjects <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.16. &amp;
<hi>Chap.</hi> 18.3. Yea it, hath a commanding power, bond and free, to receive a mark of ſubjection and ſervitude, there is none ſoe bad but will ſerve his turne, if any proue too good bee caſts them out, kills and deſtroys <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.</p>
                  <p>This is the State and Kingdome of darkenes: with which the Devill hath deluded all nations from which all Gods people &amp; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are bound in duty to ſeperate, that ſoe they may bee free from that wrath of God which ſhall fall upon the Kingdome of the beaſt to the Ruine &amp; ouerthrow thereof <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.5. &amp; 19.20. &amp; 14.9.10,11.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="differences">
            <p>Leaving the premiſes let every one note theſe enſuing differences or diſproportions, that are betwene the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Eccleſiaſticall States, for thir different natures.</p>
            <div n="1" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiasticall State</head>
                  <p>The Firſt diſproportion betweene the true and Falſe State is,<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3491:6"/>in the Originall from whence they ariſe. The true State came from Heaven and is the houſe of wiſdomes building <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.1. wherin the ſonne of God, the wiſedome of his Father, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. hath beene as faithfull as was <hi>Moſes</hi> in the former <hi>Heb.</hi>
3.2.6. &amp; is that Heaven diſcribed <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. and that Citty ſaid to come downe from Heaven <hi>Rev.</hi> 21, and is an habitation for God to dwell in, and for all his people to come into: to dwell with God their Saviour, for the name of the Citty is, the Lord is there Ezec. laſt Chap. and laſt ver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>Likewiſe it is no hard Miſtery to know the Originall of this Falſe Eccleſiaſtical State, for the Clargie, (as <hi>Goodwins Catologue of Biſhops Fox his Booke of martyrs, &amp; Rev.</hi> 9. &amp; 13 ch.) &amp; by their Preaching &amp; writing hath taught vs plainly that Antichriſt the man of linne, the ſonne of perdition is ſeated in Rome, &amp; the ſame Clergy doth alſo teach us: that their Miniſtery &amp; Goverments of
<hi>Biſhops &amp; Arch Bb.</hi> ſucceſſiuely proceedes from thence, &amp; for our confirmation herein we read that <hi>Gregory the first</hi> of that name, <hi>Pope of Rome</hi> about 1000 yeares ſince, ſent <hi>Austin the Monke</hi> into <hi>England</hi> &amp; conſecrated him <hi>firſt Arch B. of Canterbury,</hi> and he conſecrated the reſt of the Bb. and eſtabliſhed the Eccleſiaſtical ſtate, which ſtate &amp; platforme remaines vn-altered to this day, notwithſtanding the Head thereof be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. This ſtate then being the man of ſinne, it is ſaid to ariſe out of the <hi>Bottomles pitt</hi> Rev. 9.1. &amp; is called the <hi>King of the Locuſts Rev.</hi> 9.11. &amp; is ſaid to come by the effectuall working of Sathan 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2.9. and as he is the ſonne of perdition v. 3. and the Miſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity v. 7. ſo ſhall he come to confuſion by the mouth of the Lord v. 8. &amp; go to perdition <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8. as the ſonne &amp; heire thereof, &amp; he ſhall haue the company of his Fatther the great <hi>Dragon the Devill</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> with the yonger Brother the Falſe Prophet, that deceiued them that worſhipped him, theſe three ſhall dwell in the tormenting lake of Gods wrath forever and evermore
<hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. &amp; 20 10. And thus wee ſee Originally from whence hee came and whither he muſt goe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State,</head>
                  <p>A Second diſproportion is, betweene the true power and the falſe. The true power which Chriſt our King hath received of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3491:7"/>Father <hi>Math.</hi> 28.18. and hath comunicated to his Saints 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4,12. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. and to them onely; This is that Dominion that the <hi>Antient of dayes hath giuen to his Saints Dan.</hi> 7..14. compared with <hi>ver</hi> 22 27 and with <hi>Revel.</hi>
5.10. &amp; being loſt hee will recover it againe vnto them as
<hi>Daniell</hi> ſpeakes, &amp; in the New Teſtament is giuen to every Particuler viſible Church or Aſſembly of Saints <hi>Math.</hi>
18.17.19.20. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. In which point of Power, we are to note two things. Firſt the Subject or place where it doth recide, that is in the Body or Aſſembly of the Saints, as the former ſcriptures largely declare. Secondly, that they were not forced nor compelled to ſubmitt to theis power, but as the loue of God ſhed abroade in their hearts, &amp; the Doctrine of the Apoſtles by the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of the ſpirit cauſed them freely and willingly to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto it <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. for Chriſt and his Apoſtles never uſed any means to bring his ſaints into his K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngdome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>Soe in Like manner the <hi>Dragon</hi> that Old <hi>Serpent Rev.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. gave to his ſon of perdition the Beaſt, his power &amp; throne &amp; great authority Rev. 13.2. And this man of ſinne hath conveyed to all his Cergie his power; by vertue wherof, they are all rulers &amp; men of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in all nations where he hath eſtabliſhed them, as is declared <hi>Rev.</hi> 9 <hi>Chapter</hi> &amp; 10 Firſt Verſe:s wher it is ſaid, hey haue Crownes upon their heads like gold, that is counterfit power and authoritie, &amp; by vertue of this power pollitique; are made one intire body pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, under one head &amp; King ſoe called verſ. 11. and are diſtinct from the Layety, living in &amp; by the practiſe of this power, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to that Head, though they bee never ſoe farre diſperced or remote from him; this beeing obſerved, the diſproportion will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in theſe two particulers.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the ſubject place where this power doth recide, it beeing in the body of the Clergy, the Layety being excluded though never ſo high or great in place, as Iudges, Iuſtices, Lords &amp; Knights &amp;c, they refuſing it as a matter not belonging to them, but to the Clergy.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, this power compells all in all nations, will they nill they to come under this Government, and to obey his power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<hi>Rev.</hi> 13,8.16. where it is ſaid, he made all great and ſmall, rich
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3491:7"/>and poore, free and bond, to ſubmit to him, elſe they ſhould not buy nor ſell nor live ver. 17. and ch 11 7.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>A Third diſproportion ſhall app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in this, Every Kingdome or pollitique ſtate whether Civill or Eccleſiaſticall, hath their ſeverall bookes and Charters: wherein is contayned the Platforme of there ſeverall governments, ſoe every Church is knowne by its owne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, Cannons, and Conſtitutions, ſo that they that will know what Church, Miniſtery and worſhip Chriſt and his Apoſtles hath planted in the new Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment after the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>remoniall was aboliſhed, they muſt read the Acts of the Apoſtles with the Epiſtles <hi>Acts,</hi> 16.4. 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22 18.19. Yea the whole new Teſtemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and there they ſhall finde Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and King, his Bookes of Cannons, Articles and Ordination, to guide and direct the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the ſaints in his Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me vnto the end of the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiasticall State</head>
                  <p>Alſo in the Falſe State, they that would know what goverment, Church, Miniſtery, and worſhip, the man of ſinne hath eſtabliſhed, he muſt viewe his Platforme contayned in his Booke of Cannons, Articles, and Ordintion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the <hi>Priests</hi> &amp; <hi>Deacons,</hi> his Bookes of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>milies and Common Prayers, for in them is contayned thoſe inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, Lawes and ordinances that he hath eſtabliſhed, but how con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtement; they that are Spirituall in part doe know, and how obedience to them is infor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced and divine Lawes omitted and laid aſide, the poore ſaints doe finde, and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e to there ſmart.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State</head>
                  <p>A Fourth Diſproportion. This State makes not Nationall nor Provinciall pollitique Bodies, but only particuler Congregations or aſſemblies of Saints, as in <hi>Judea</hi> one Nation; yet divers Churches
<hi>Gal.</hi> 1.22. Soe <hi>Galalia</hi> one nation yet many Churches ver. 3. like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Aſia</hi> hath ſeaven ſeuerall Churches <hi>ver</hi>
1.11. and where there was but one the Holi ghoſt ſpeakes in the ſinguler number, as the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> another at <hi>Corinth,</hi> another at
<hi>Colloſſia,</hi> another at <hi>Theſſaloniea,</hi> and the like.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the Congregations of our Lord Chriſt come freely and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3491:8"/>willingly as ſo many living ſtones 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
2.4.5. volluntarily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>iting themſelues together, whereby they become <hi>A Spirituall houſe and a Royall Prieſthood ver.</hi> 9. and are hereby capable of performing the publique worſhip of the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament, wherein they are to offer as <hi>Living ſacrifices their Soules and Bodies Rom.</hi> 12.1. and by faith to haue Communion with their Mediator <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to all ſuch aſſemblies gathered in his name and power
<hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. <hi>Math.</hi> 18 19.20. which is the forme and beeing of this their viſible and pollitique vnion &amp; communion <hi>Ephe.</hi>
2.20.21.22. <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.19. Thirdly, the viſible Churches of Chriſt are independent Bodies, there is Equallity or apparity amongſt them: that is, they are all alike in Iuriſdiction &amp; authority, they are all Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. they are every one of them a Ieruſalem compact together within it ſelfe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.3. compared with
<hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. hauing each of them whole Chriſt for their mediatour, that is, <hi>Prieſt, Prophet,</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> and thereby enjoy all his power and all his promiſes, and all his Lawes and ordinances, with all his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and previledges.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly and Laſtly; in the vſe of their liberty which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy from and vnder Chriſt their Head, and dwels in the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in the vſe whereof they are inabled to exclude ſinne and ſinners and ought that offends God or them, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. 2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 3.14
<hi>Acts</hi> 3 and to eſtabliſh among them ſuch Officers, Ordinances, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtrations as their Lord &amp; King hath given them for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and profit, by this power they can examine and try Falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. they can reproue and admoniſh proud ones and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the negligent <hi>Coll,</hi> 4.17, thus their power and liberty from Chriſt their head, becomes a great benefit and a great good to the whole body, in theſe and divers others perticulers of great weight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>But this Falſe State brings ten Kingdomes into one pollitique body <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12.13.15. &amp; hath ſet heads over nations to bring them into pollitique bodies Eccleſiaſticall, as for example,
<hi>England</hi> is one pollitique body Eccleſiaſticall, (as well as Civil) vnder one <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, and Pope of Lambeth,</hi> and by the ſinewes and bonds of his Eccleſiaſticall power the whole hand as one body is<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3491:8"/>knitt and bound to that Eccleſiaſticall Head, by vertue of that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh authority that hee ſucceſſively doth exerciſe, and hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Austin</hi> the <hi>Monke,</hi> who conſecrated, authorized &amp; ſent into this Land to eſtabliſh this power according to
<hi>Pope Gregorius</hi> his will wiſdome and power.</p>
                  <p>Farther, this Falſe State hath left noe liberty nor power to any perſon good or bad <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7.8. but compels and forces all in the name and power of Antichriſts ſucceſſours, will they nill they, haue they faith or no, conſcience or no conſcience, this beaſt will be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and obeyed of all ſtates degrees and conditions, of all people in the world ver. 15.16.17. ſoe that there is noe Eccleſiaſticall body of his making whether it be the great <hi>Catholique Babylon, Reuel.</hi> 16.19. or Nationall, or Provinciall; or Perrochiall bodies, but this Beaſt firſt made or framed them, and ſtill by the force of the ſame authority doth compell them to aſſemble and worſhip in his name and power, which power is the tome and being of their viſible &amp; pollitique vnion and Communion.</p>
                  <p>Againe the viſible Churches which are in the Kingdome of the Beaſt, are neither independent nor free bodies, therefore the great Citty is called by the Holy ghoſt; <hi>Sodome</hi> &amp; <hi>Egypt:</hi> for her filthynes &amp; bondage <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. ſo that there hath not in Europe one parriſh beene found free from ſpirituall Egyptian bondage inflicted upon them by ſome taſke Maſter of the Clergy, as the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Church-Wardens,</hi> who force and drive (by ſpirituall tyranny ouer the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men) to their falſely ſo called ſpirituall Courts, to whom they are in bondage, and vpon whom they do eſſencially depend, &amp; ſo are not independent, neither haue they any power, or liberty to procure truth or abandon Errour in their publicke worſhip.</p>
                  <p>And Laſtly, theſe poore Captiuated ſlaviſh aſſemblies haue noe liberty or power of Chriſt among them, but a great power ouer them that keepes them in a ſpirituall bondage, and there aſſemblies conſiſts of ſinners of all ſorts, for they haue noe power of reproving or excluding ſinne or ſinners, they muſt take ſuch officers as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſends them be they never ſoe bad; and they haue noe power to exclude or refuſe them, and if they proue good they haue no power to keepe them neyther, canne they keepe themſelves there, except they ſubmit to, and practiſe ſuch ordinances, Lawes &amp; adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3491:9"/>as are the inventions of men and will worſhip, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ſo breake the ſecond commandement, ſo that they haue no power to do them ſelves any ſpirituall good, or to exclude from themſelves any ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall evill or hurt, but being injoyned by there ſpirituall taſke-maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to aſſemble to Church, they goe, and when they preſent them to their Courts, they runne, &amp; being commanded to do this or that in there publick worſhip, they doe it, though it bee contrary to God and there own conſciences In theſe and divers other particulers this power, that is ouer them is to their exceding great hurt &amp; damage.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>The Fift Diſproportionly s in their Officers or miniſters, which we are to obſerve thus.</p>
                  <p>Firſt in there number, Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and King hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and ordayned onely fiue; which are ſpecified <hi>Rom.</hi>
12.7.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. for though our Lord hath ordained in his Church for the Foundation thereof; himſelfe being the Cheife cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone, Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts, yet not ſucceſſivelie continued; but theſe Five onelie are to continue to the End of the world.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, theſe Officers and Miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt, haue not onely there authority from the particuler congregation, but do ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally and naturally ariſe out of the ſame <hi>Acts,</hi> 1.23,26, and
6.3; &amp; 14.23. <hi>Note that in the new Tranſlation the word Election is left out of the</hi> 23. <hi>verſe.</hi> For before there be any Officers in the Church the e is inſtituted by the Holy Ghoſt divine
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffices; functions or odminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions; as voyd and empty roomes. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 122.5.
<hi>Rev.</hi> 4.4, &amp; cha. 20.4. for the ſaints which dwell in that Citty of God to ſupply with fit &amp; able perſons, to performe thoſe ſeverall adminiſtrations, which God hath ordayned and commanded them, and for the authoriſing of their Officers, they haue Chriſt walking a mongſt them as in one of his golden Candleſticks, holding them in the right hand of his Kingly authority, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.16. by theſe divine deputies he rules them as a King, teacheth them as a Prophet, and feedes them as a Prieſt with his moſt ſacred body and bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The falſe Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>But the officers of this falſe ſtate are the whole body of the Clergy<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3491:9"/>almoſt innumerable if we ſhould reckon their ſeverall orders &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>diſtinction of degres, as <hi>Pope, Cardinals, Patriarchs, Primates, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>trapolitans, Arch-biſhops, Lord-biſhops, Deanes, Chancellars, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar-Generals, Praebends, Arch-deacons, Subdeacons, Doctors, of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Law, Doctors of Divinity, Proctors, Regiſters, Cannons, Petty-Cannons, Chanters, Preists, Ieſuits, Pariſh-Preists, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, Deacons, Veſtremen, Church Wardens, Swornemen, Sidemen, Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſh-Clarkes, Sextons, Purſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uants, Summinours, Apparitors,</hi> with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multitude more which would tire a man to reckon them al up their being well nie ſixſcore in all of this rabble, and as Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles never knew them nor approvedly ſpoke of them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave warning to the Saints that they ſhould take heede of ſuch, for ſuch were to come 2 <hi>Pet.</hi>
2.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. and the Saints haue wofull experience that they are come: for they haue been pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued with them this thouſand yeares &amp; more, Yet the time approch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth and is neere when they ſhall bee conſumed with the Breath of his mouth and brightneſſe of his comming 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2.8,
<hi>that rides vpon the white Horſe Rev.</hi> 19.11,12,15, for their Kingdome is momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and his is Everlaſting.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe theſe offices riſe not out of the particuler aſſemblies, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue the aſſemblies any offices or functions, properly in them nor any power or authority to produce or raiſe officers out of them ſelves, for the Clergy are a perticuler body diſtinct from the Laye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hauing their conſecrations, Offices and authority from and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, and ſoe ſent by their Eccleſiaſticall Heads, and bring their Office and authority with them, as matters not belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the aſſemblyes, and ſo by vertue of that Eccleſiaſticall power rule ouer them as Lords and teacheth them as that power allowes, and commands them, vſurpedly adminiſtreth ſpirituall foode vnto them, and ſoe by Imitation beguileth the ſimple and affronts the Adminiſtration of the mediatourſhip of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>A Sixt Diſproportion is the difference betweene there Lawes and Adminiſtrations, as euery Citty and Corporation haue there Lawes amongſt themſelues by vertue of their Charters from their King, Even ſoe hath every viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le Church from Chriſt there King,<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3491:10"/>by vertue of their Charter, which is the New Teſtament, in poſſeſſion amongſt themſelves all Lawes &amp; ordinances as Chriſt by his Apoſtles <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. hath committed to them, Charging them vnder acurſe to keep from adding or diminiſhing to or from theſe divine Lawes <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2.2. 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15 <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as the difference is great in the number of there Offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers, the true being few &amp; the Falſe being innumerable, ſo of nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity muſt the difference be in the lawes and adminiſtrations agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the number of Officers; which particulers I muſt omitt as a matter to large for this place, yet note this by the way: that one of the firſt laws in Chriſts Church is the ordinance of Prophecie 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
14.1. to the end of the <hi>chap.</hi> that is, that it is not only the liberty, but the duty of every man in the Church that is able to teach &amp; preach to the edifying of the body, ſo to do (provided he keep the propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of fayth; that is the boundes of his owne knowledge <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiasticall State.</head>
                  <p>But as hath beene formerly ſaid; the falſe Church hath no power nor Charter nor office, for all theſe things are locked up within the body of the Clergie, ſoe is it as true that they are diſtitute of all lawes or adminiſtrations, amongſt themſelves, ſo that all they haue at any time is brought to them by theſe Crowned Stinging meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of that authority, as Common ſence and reaſon proveth:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat the Clergie being a pollitique and diſtinct body of themſelves from the Layety; hauing all power and authority Eccleſiaſticall in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, muſt of neceſſity haue all lawes ordinances and adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in themſelves, whether they bee divine, (which they haue by vſurpato<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) or humane, by their own Inventio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they only poſeſſe them and haue power to vſe them not fearing adding, or detracting, the Lay congregations being altogether paſſive herein til their Jnju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion make them active.</p>
                  <p>Soe the lawes and ordinances of this ſtate being innumerable (as their officers are) J muſt omit for to name them, as their ſeverall falſe holy things: Kneeling in the &amp; of receiuing, Signeing with, the Croſſe in Baptiſme, Churching of women, Reading Prayers, with the Conſecrating of Dayes, Times, Places, Perſons, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with their Anoynting of the Sicke, and vnholy Orders of<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3491:10"/>conſecration, with other innumerable inventions, not worthy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place in Chriſtians thoughts, onely note the oppoſition of their law againſt the law of Chriſt, in vehement prohibiting and ſtrongly barring all (Lay men as they call them) from preaching, that let Chriſt giue never ſoe great abillities or guifts to lay men: they are never ſuffered to make any publique vſe of them, but it is horrible prophaneſſe and ſacrelegious preſumption ſoe to doe, and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of the Clergie is and hath been ſo vniuerſall: that it reacheth to the foure Corners of the earth, and with holdeth this ſpirituall winde of Chriſt Jeſus in the mouth of his Saints that it ſhall not blow upon them that are in the earth <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="disproportion">
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The true Eccleſiasticall State</head>
                  <p>A Sevevth Diſproportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is betwixt their ſubjects or members, the ſubjects or members of Chriſts Kingdome
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Church muſt, be beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſciples, they muſt bee Saints by Calling &amp; ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. they muſt be liuing ſtones to build his houſe withall 1 <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
2.5. ſuch as theſe and theſe onely are enjoyned to obſerves whatſoever he commands them, to theſe only is his Kingdome and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> given, theſe be they that are crowned as Kings, anoynted as Prieſts, the mediatour himſelfe being theirs, &amp; he hath committed the adminiſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ion of his mediatorſhip in his Church to them. <hi>But to the Wicked ſaith God, what hast thou to do with theſe things. Pſa.</hi> 50.16. <hi>Thou haſt not a wedding garment therefore binde him hand &amp; foote &amp; caſt him out as leaven dangerous to hurt the body</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>For without ſhall be &amp; dogges inchanters and thoſe that loue &amp; make lyes Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>But within there ſhall be noe vncleane thing. Revel.</hi> 21.27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="state">
                  <head>The Falſe Eccleſiaſticall State.</head>
                  <p>But the Subjects of this foule body are all vncleane and hatefull birds, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.2. the Cage that holds them being the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſtate of Rome, is become the habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Devils &amp; the hold of every foul ſpirit, ſo that the vnfit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſts members which they can leaſt indure or ſuffer amongſt them, are the conſcious ſaints, they are the ſooneſt turned out, cut of and killed by them <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.15, but yet if the ſaints; or Chriſt himſelfe can by temptations or compul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion bee drawn to worſhip the Devill, he will haue it of them <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.9. for he will haue all the world to worſhip him, if high and low, rich and<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3491:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Poore, bond and free, be all the world, he will compell them to bee ſubjects or members in his black Regiment <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.16.17.</p>
                  <p>For theſe dwell and rule make &amp; change lawes and times in this their habition which is the bottemleſſe pit, as the Father Sonne &amp; holy Ghoſt do in their habitation, which is the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="definition">
            <head>The true definition of a true viſible Church of Ieſus Christ.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat every true viſible Church of Chriſt, are a company of people called and ſeperated out of the world, <hi>(a)</hi> By the word of God, Ioyned <hi>(b)</hi> together in the fellowſhip of the Goſpell by volentary <hi>(c)</hi> profeſſion of fayth and obedience of Chriſt
<hi>(a) Levit.</hi> 20.26. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 10,18. <hi>Ezeche.</hi> 44; 7.9. 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.10. <hi>Act,</hi> 2.40. <hi>Act,</hi> 19.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
1.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4. <hi>(b) Act.</hi> 11.21.23.
<hi>Ier.</hi> 50.4,5. <hi>(c) Act.</hi> 2.41.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That every true viſible Church of Chriſt, is an independent bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of it ſelfe <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.3. chapt. &amp; hath power from Chriſt her head <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.18.24. to bind &amp; looſe; to receive in &amp; caſt out by the Keys of the Kingdome <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17.18.
<hi>Pſa.</hi> 149.8.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.5.12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That Jeſus Chriſt hath by his Laſt wil and Teſtament given vnto and ſett in his Church, ſufficient rodinary Officers: with their quallifications Callings and worke, for the Adminiſtration of his holy things, and for the ſufficient ordinary Inſtruction, Guidance and ſervice of his Church to the end of the world. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6.7.8. <hi>Ephe.</hi>
4.11.12.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.8. <hi>&amp; Chapt.</hi>
5.9.10. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3. And that all the Officers in the Church are but onely five and noe more namely <hi>Paſtor, Teacher, Elder, Deacons, Widdows. Rom.</hi> 12.7.8. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.
<hi>&amp; Ch.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.7.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3491:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
